[Music]
hi everybody I'd like to introduce a
conversation I had recently with Greg
Thomas about the killing of George Floyd
and the resulting protests in the u.s.
Greg has been on the channel before he
is a scholar of black American issues
he's also a jazz critic and an integral
theorist and when we originally met it
was to discuss Greg's work around using
jazz as a technique to achieve
collective intelligence and we featured
that conversation in a film called lost
ways of knowing I was really happy to
catch up with him and I hope you enjoy
the conversation so Greg Thomas welcome
back to the channel it's it's good to
have you back Thank You Ellie glad to be
back Greg you are you're an integral
scholar and a jazz critic and a writer
among other hats you wear you're also a
speaker at the rebel ISM festival last
weekend and during the festival in in
one of your sessions you talked about
what we're seeing in the u.s. right now
the horrific killing of George Floyd and
the resulting protests that have sprung
up so I just wanted to start there and
just just check in and ask how you felt
when you first heard about what that
murder the first thought was he would go
again
and then not again
it would gets like a scab on a wound
that heals and gets torn off time and
time again so and this is when I heard
about it this is before I even saw it so
it was it was infuriating it was
something that it was such a graphic
display of so many the dynamics not only
the relationship between
bad policing and the black American
community but power dynamics the the
incredibly callous it wasn't the callous
casual approach that he took he had his
hands in his pocket as he was choking
the life out of him with his knee and
he's looking around seeing the people
who's who's saying to him look I mean he
says I can't breathe with you and he
keeps on going
so it's angering and saddening as I said
in the piece that you referenced so
right now how about how do I feel I feel
I feel kind of somber but I also feel
hopeful and that's because I'm gonna
tell you a quick story this morning I
read what his six-year-old daughter
Jorge floored six-year-old daughter said
she said my daddy has changed the world
and it brought me to tears man this
little girl who's gonna grow up without
a father can see the uprising the
rebelling the protests that have been
generated through his violent death
coupled with armored augury
Brianna Taylor and a great list of
others that it's like enough is enough
you know but one of the things that
makes me hopeful
a couple of things one the young people
who are with risen up as young people
tend to do generation after generation
so that gives me hope I am really
inspired by not only the working-class
and intellectual is responding to what
has been going on and raising their
voices but leaders of other sectors of
the society CEOs leaders in their fields
and industries speaking out and speaking
up that's that's something that wouldn't
necessarily expect it I don't think it's
really happened before like this and
also what gives me hope is knowing how
how life and culture work that our
reality as human beings isn't just
physical it's also symbolic and Joey as
a symbol is not only a victim his
daughter was right he is going to help
change the world because he's a tragic
hero tragic heroes die but they still
are heroes and he's sacrificed his life
and he will be remembered and the world
can change if we keep working towards it
so so you're a you're a scholar black
American issues in history in particular
Albert Murray and Ralph Ellison now
there's a it seems obviously I mean
there is a shared trajectory and story
leading us right up until this point
right now I'm curious to get your
thoughts on what's different or what do
you what do you feel is different about
the culture that injustice is like this
are happening and now and the response
to it compared to say in Ellis memories
day yeah they came of age really in the
midst of the late 50s and 60s where of
course you had the civil rights movement
the sixties where for the first time
because of Technology
you have new services actually covering
protests and because of the brilliant
genius strategy of non-violent protest
by dr. Martin Luther King jr. and SCLC
and other organizations you had a the
taping of just incredible racist
responses to kids trying to go to school
to people trying to vote you have four
little girls being blown up in a church
in Alabama you know you have like
that going on but dr. King knew that and
he was influenced by Gandhi he was
influenced by Emerson and many others
you know he's a very learned man he knew
that if it were violent one black folks
would be slaughtered okay you don't go
up against an enemy that it that out
man's you and that is itching
hysterically itching to wipe you out you
don't do that so they took the moral
high ground and you saw black folks you
know being water hosed being in a trying
to sit in a counter and being hit and
had milks poured over them and worse so
that was the first instance where the
media raised the consciousness of the
country and the world in such a way that
people are like whoa no no no no no no
just saying right leading to in 1965 the
passing of the Civil Rights Act and such
you fast forward to today you start with
say Rodney King in 1990 California
with his brutal beating by officers and
then them getting off you know on up to
today where we all it ain't just the
news media we know we are not one of
these and folks are taping stuff and
it's being put up on social media and
spreading virally around the world in no
time so that's the similarity well some
of the differences of what I mentioned
earlier I have never seen in so many
sectors of the society in so many levels
of the society a common voice though of
course they're folks who are focusing
more on the looting and rioting which I
call violent protest and rebellion which
I'm not I don't concur with that you've
got you know small businesses in black
neighborhoods being destroyed but also I
recognize that some of the people doing
that are not necessarily from those
areas or from the community you got
folks I think on the right and the left
who want to foment chaos for their own
ends okay but you got folks who focused
on that and also then the violent tragic
deaths that precipitated the protests
we've talked about the two figures you
you were talking about earlier
Albert Murray and not Ellison as sort of
proto integral thinkers and if we get to
explore that a bit but just just first
off for anyone kind of not familiar with
integral theory why why do you feel it's
a useful frame for looking at you know
race identity culture as a whole and why
is it useful now in particular yeah for
me into the theory is like a heuristic
it's a it's a way to frame map and model
reality on different levels so you take
the fall
audience of aqua all quadrants all
levels that King Wilbur talks about the
the four quadrants are the inner and
outer dimensions of individual and
collective reality individual people us
as persons so if you have on the top two
you have on the left side the upper left
the subjective realm the realm of our
thoughts you know the inner part of us
as individuals then on the right the
upper right you've got our bodies our
brains and such right and on the lower
left you've got the inner dimension of
groups and then on the lower right
you've got the inner dimensions of
social dynamics social structures you
could look at race through those
quadrants so one of the things that I
have started to say is that to be an
anti-racist
you have to I think interrogate and
critique the very concept of race
integral theory is powerful because it
gives you a way to critique race as a
theory and as a biological reality while
acknowledging that it does find its
place and land in other dimensions of
life so that's one perspective and one
important way of looking at race through
integral Theory another is developmental
theory which in the last I guess 30
years I'm really - my adult
developmental theory for the most part
Carol Gilligan
Robert Keegan Suzanne Cooke Gruyter and
others who have developed different
theories of adult human development but
even without those there are certain
developmental theories that we can take
a look at that are very helpful in
understanding race okay so if you take
one particular trajectory traditional
modern postmodern integral or same
edimar
race which has to do with outer
appearance phenotypic appearance right
at the ethnocentric stage if someone
looks differently whoa that's like hmm
you know that's another then we get to
the modern stage hey let's get
scientific let's look at race as as
whether or not it's actually a reality
biologically no then you get to
post-modernism and it says but racism is
a social construction yes and you get to
integral and you say you know something
as an index to human reality in terms of
someone's intelligence
it's almost potential so it don't mean
nothing
how you gonna judge somebody based on
their outer appearance the way they look
it is ludicrous but it's been
particularly snow with the advent of the
slave trade in Europe as it came from
parts of Europe to the Americas you know
it ended up becoming when you added it
to the you know theory of evolution not
as Darwin proposed it but as some people
took his theory and used it to their own
ends you have what they call scientific
racism scientific justification for it
in the mythological sphere you have you
know darkness being viewed as akin to
the devil and likeness being akin to all
this good that that's overlaid right
another way integral looks at it is
through the lens of like ethnocentric
identity to more of a regional or
national identity to a world sent to a
cosmos century identity and as you have
these wider circles of care concern
identification the less and less you're
likely to be behold into a theory such
as race which is something Ralph Ellison
called blood thinking that's
ethnocentric thinking that you know you
have certain qualities of yourself
because you're a member of a certain
group and you have a certain blood and
those qualities in the blood you know
the the hot you know Italia is now the
thing is these are stereotypes which and
the thing about stereotypes as they say
it has some similar sub truths but you
don't have to use it in an invidious way
you can use it as a way of appreciation
appreciating excuse me the ethnic
diversity and various styles and ways
people move and live and talk and and
and dance and eat in the world you have
an appreciation for difference in that
way you know so I used integral theory
to critique race in those ways and my
particular focus really is centered in
the lower-left a cultural dimension in
particular as that's the place I think
of meaning and tools of values and
principles of lifestyles based on those
values that manifest as ways of being in
the world and ways of creating art and
other tools or technologies in the world
technologies that Alba Mary said are
survival tools that then are transmuted
through your experience into play
through play into art hmm that's great
just to dive into something a little bit
because I think it's worth I'm thinking
and this is a really good point about
integral giving us a kind of heuristic
and a way to see things in different
quadrants because a big part of the the
anger right now and traditionally in
culture when when one group is treated
unfairly is that it is both a social
construct but it's a live reality and
you saw that you sort of touched
so how does integral help us explain
maps it always I think it's been I think
for many people there's a kind of
tension there but it sounds like you're
saying that in a way it's it's in one
area to social construct from the kind
of individual level but then in the
level of culture for example what we're
seeing right now is the culture going
through sort of a process of hopefully
healing misconception is that there are
there around race and the way they
manifest so it seems like kind of both
are happening in some ways I correctly
no I think you are and see from an
integral perspective integral is
supposed to be able to look at the what
they call first tier value means and
look at the pros and cons of each so you
know from pre-modern to modern to
postmodern to second tier right so if
that's the case we can look at the
postmodern critique of see the
postmodern critique of race and the
social construction it's also a critique
of the efficacy of recognizing that race
biologically is not real they're like
you always have them say okay that's
true but but but social structures and
systemic racism that's true but I think
we need to acknowledge always
acknowledge because we need a a platform
from which we can look at some human
commonalities right true human
commonality so if we don't say he raised
human race you don't stop there and your
analysis you have to look at the systems
of oppression that have been replicated
and instantiated through the education
system healthcare the legal system yes
but you can't stay there I think it's
really important I think this is where
the struggle is gone I was having
conversation with Diane with Joe
Hamilton the other day and she made the
statement she said you know when you
look at the struggle particularly from
the 60s there have been a lot of
advances and
putting into the legal system things
that outlaw you know out now
discrimination based on your identity to
different identity markers that's true
she says but I think the I think the
struggle and now what we're seeing in
the world it's it's on the left side
it's in the interiors now that we're
actually doing the battle so I think the
I these basically you know over the
weekend over rebel ISM Festival both in
the Jazz presentation and in the Ellison
Murray continuum presentation and in the
in the panel discussion I referenced the
I we it which is a nice short for the
four quadrants you know the I being the
personal and subjective the we being the
inter subjective the it being the
individual externals and the collective
external of the social structures but
you just put it in it so if the battle
is in the I we face then that's where we
need to focus primarily yes acknowledge
and fight those battles in terms of the
systems and structures but each of us as
individuals and in working in with other
people need to look at how can we make
things better what what are the barriers
that get in the way of us making things
better what are the good things from the
ethnocentric stage the myth or poetic
dynamic which is kind of you know
modernism came and says no no that's not
rationally or scientifically true but
human beings need that you are not going
to get away from myth and ritual you're
not or if you do you end up in some you
know place of like enemy or just not
having a grounding which a lot of people
feel so we need that what we don't need
from the ethnocentric is the xenophobic
fear of the other and that been
manifesting into violence so yeah that
so integral allows us to balance these
things on
way to look at the pros and cons embrace
the pros and work together with others
towards the better wonderful wonderfully
said so just just before we finish Greg
you have any is there anything we didn't
cover anything you want to express yeah
anything at all oh I'll use some words
from the movement keep the faith
a luta continua the struggle continues
know that the battle is not going to be
won ultimately in a week a month a year
that this struggle this epic struggle
and Frederick Douglass said that without
struggle there is no progress that this
struggle is a ongoing struggle because
it's not just a struggle against
oppressive structures this is a struggle
against mindsets that people have and
having have inherited generationally ok
speaking of generationally I would also
like to say to my people my ethnic
cultural kin that our struggle has been
an epic struggle an epic and heroic
struggle and that though we have been
victimized wages victims and that is
important for us to know that we have
agency and responsibility also and it's
not just about what others can do to
change themselves or speaking of the
others some others do need to change
themselves and for my fellow Americans
who and outside of America to those
folks from America who identify as white
as a racial identity
I suggest asking yourself some questions
what does being white mean to me
what does whiteness mean to me I
disagree with the post modernist
perspective of antifragility that says
that if you're white so you used to be
if you're white you're right
if you're brown stay down if you're
black you know hold back or something
like that you know but now it's like if
you're white you're in from certain
activists and academics if you're white
you are automatically guilty and what
Albert Murray said is you know as a
strategy for engaging with people guilt
is not the best strategy intelligent
action is a much better a strategic
approach but I would ask folks who
consider themselves white to ask them
certain themselves certain questions and
I want to leave as I like to do with a
point of hope I do not agree with my
postmodern friends who suggest that if
you are white not only are you guilty
you are you are beholden to a history of
oppression that means that white
supremacy reign supreme no that makes no
distinction between white privilege
white superiority and white in white
supremacy is the overuse of the word Rai
supremacy and Albert Murray called it
the folklore of white supremacy unless
you believe that white supremacy is
actually real then they'll just be
saying white supremacy white supremacy
you cuss like a mantra you know but
white folks do need to look at
themselves so it's a conversation that
quote unquote white people need to have
amongst themselves and it's a
conversation that we need to have
together
so we can then create through empathetic
listening and generative listening Oh
to create a better future together
so this of inquiry that has to happen
most people don't like to do it most
people don't like to to do that kind of
self-reflection because it's not easy
it's not is it's painful you know but
not only without struggles then no
progress without some pain and learning
there is no growth I was also really
struck by you know when we spoken before
is is that that combination of utter
injustice and hopelessness and despair
and hope and you've talked about that in
relation to the Blues and I'm not being
so fundamental to the black American
experience love to just hear hear what
it is about the blues then what was the
blues attitude to that well the Blues is
as Ralph Ellison once said in order by
autobiographical chronicle of a
catastrophe expressed lyrically that's
one as a poetic kind of description his
his partner and and dear friend and
comrade in the struggle
Albert Murray who was a mentor of mine
as I said in the rebel ISM festival he
coined a phrase called the Blues idiom
and the Blues idiom to Murray was a way
a that black Americans confronted
absurdity oppression existence itself so
it's an existential perspective on life
that says life is a low-down dirty shame
that's a fact but you know something
we're going to be as intentional and
purposeful as we can we're going to be
clear on our goals and objectives and
our visions and we're going to work
towards it it says that we are going
to develop the kind of skill sets and
heart sets and soul sets that will give
us the wherewithal to withstand the
slings and arrows of outrageous fortune
and with those skills and the individual
excellence that in the model that my
apartment of wife Jill and I have you
don't do it just as a heroic individual
you do it as a heroic collective you do
it with other people in such a way that
you can make things better so the Blues
acknowledges the lowdown dirty shameless
of life it doesn't ignite the diamond
ayat repress it it says it as the
Thelonious Monk song says straight no
chaser but at the same time we're going
to acknowledge recognize and embrace joy
even if it's momentary we're going to
kind of dance we're gonna have we're
gonna express ourselves with our bodies
with that embodied cognition and we are
going to celebrate and affirm the very
reality and existence of life itself and
my kinfoke black folks do that very well
which is why to Ralph Ellison monstro he
says you know for the blues the
spirituals the jazz the dance is what we
had in place of freedom in place of
social political and economic freedom
but we expressed our as culturally
that's why I look to culture is such a
powerful place for the responses to life
and to injustice that that not only we
as a people but that I mean the Blues is
something that may have originated and
did originate with black Americans but
the Blues is universal you know you know
in Buddhism
talk about you know life is suffering
that's the bluesman you know so it's
something that you know is rooted yet
can be embraced and should be embracing
the fact has been embraced by people
around the world embrace the blues and
jazz which is the as Murray says the
extension elaboration and the fine knit
of of the Blues aesthetic Greg Thomas
thank you you're welcome
thank you man rebel wisdom was set up to
make sense of the world at a deeper
level than the mainstream media it was
built for these times of crisis and
change which is why we want to do what
we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom Jim a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching see you soon
you